<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2012-2013) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2012-2013) -->

<section anchor="sec:intro" title="Introduction">
  <t>
    Mandatory Access Control (MAC) (<xref target='RFC4949' />) systems have been mainstreamed in
    modern operating systems such as Linux, FreeBSD, and Solaris.
    MAC systems bind security attributes to
    subjects (processes) and objects within a system.  These attributes
    are used with other information in the system to make access control
    decisions.
  </t>

  <t>
    Access control models such as Unix permissions or Access Control
    Lists are commonly referred to as Discretionary Access Control (DAC)
    models.  These systems base their access decisions on user identity
    and resource ownership.  In contrast MAC models base their access
    control decisions on the label on the subject (usually a process) and
    the object it wishes to access.  These labels may contain user
    identity information but usually contain additional information.  In
    DAC systems users are free to specify the access rules for resources
    that they own.  MAC models base their security decisions on a system
    wide policy established by an administrator or organization which the
    users do not have the ability to override.  DAC systems offers some
    protection against unauthorized users running malicious software.
    However, even an authorized user can execute malicious or flawed software
    with those programs running with the full permissions of the user executing it.
    Inversely MAC models can confine malicious or flawed software and
    usually act at a finer granularity than their DAC counterparts.
  </t>

  <t>
    Besides describing the requirements, this document records the
    functional requirements for the client imposed by the pre-existing
    security models on the client. This document may help those outside the
    NFS community understand those issues.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor='sec:defs' title='Definitions'>
  <t>
    <list style='hanging'>
      <t hangText='Foreign Label:'>
        is when a MAC implementation encounters a label in a format other 
        than it uses for encoding.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Label Format Specifier (LFS):'>
        is an identifier used by the client to establish
        the syntactic format of the security label and the semantic meaning
        of its components.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Label Format Registry:'>
        is the IANA registry (see <xref target="lfsreg" />) containing all registered
        LFS along with references to the documents that
        describe the syntactic format and semantics of the security label.
      </t>

      <t hangText='MAC-Aware:'>
        is a server which can transmit and store object labels.
      </t>

      <t hangText='MAC-Functional:'>
        is a client or server which is Labeled NFS enabled. Such a system can interpret labels and
        apply policies based on the security system.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Multi-Level Security (MLS):'>
        is a traditional model where objects are given a sensitivity
        level (Unclassified, Secret, Top Secret,  etc) and a category set
        <xref target='RH_MLS' />.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Object:'>
        is a passive resource within the system that we
        wish to be protected.  Objects can be entities such as files,
        directories, pipes, sockets, and many other system resources relevant
        to the protection of the system state.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Policy Identifier (PI):'>
        is an optional part of the definition of a Label
        Format Specifier which allows for clients and server to identify
        specific security policies.
      </t>

      <t hangText='Subject:'>
        is an active entity, usually a process, which is
        requesting access to an object.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <section title="Requirements Language">
    <t>
      The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
      &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
      &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
      &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
      interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
